Register of the Marx Lewis Papers, 1907-1988.
Hoover Institution Archives
Marx Lewis Papers,
1907-1988
88029
Lewis, Marx, 1897-1990.
26 manuscript boxes (10.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, bulletins, newsletters, press releases, resolutions, trial transcripts, pamphlets, and clippings, relating to the 1919 trial of Victor Berger under the Espionage Act; Socialist Party internal politics, especially during the mid-1930s; post-World War II opposition to communism within American trade unions; and anti-communist activities of the Council Against Communist Aggression and its successor organization, the Council for the Defense of Freedom.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Berger, Victor L., 1860-1929.; Socialism--United States.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.; Socialist Party (U.S.); Trade-unions and communism.; Anti-communist movements--United States.; Council for the Defense of Freedom (U.S.); United States--Politics and government.; World War, 1914-1918.; Subversive activities--United States.; Trade-unions--United States.
Biographical Note.
1897, December 28 Born, Brooklyn, New York
1917-1919, Secretary to Representative Meyer London
1919-1920 Associate Editor, New York Call
1923-1929 Secretary to Representative Victor Berger
1929-c. 1934 Lawyer, Washington, D.C.
1934-1938 Executive Secretary, United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers International Union
1938-1939 Deputy Treasurer, City of New York
1939-1949 Executive Vice President, United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers International Union
1949-1960 General Secretary-Treasurer, United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers International Union
1950- Chairman, Council Against Communist Aggression (subsequently known as the Council for the Defense of Freedom)
Marx Lewis was a member of the Board of Directors of the League for Industrial Democracy; he was Chairman of the National Legislative Committee, Liberal Party of New York State for l4 years, as well as a member of its State Executive and Trade Union Committees; and he was on the Labor Advisory Committee of the National Labor Service, American Jewish Committee.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1926-1977. (Box No. 1.)
  Clippings, biographical sketches, and miscellany. Arranged chronologically.
- Correspondence File, 1916-1986. (Box No. 1-2.)
  Correspondence, memorandum, miscellany, clippings, and letters to the editor by Marx Lewis and Norman Thomas. NOTE: Includes letters neither to nor from Marx Lewis; most of these were generated primarily by Arthur McDowell, Executive Secretary-Treasurer, Council Against Communist Aggression. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
- Speeches and Writings, 1923-1986. (Box No. 2.)
  Typescripts and printed copies by Marx Lewis, and related material, including correspondence, a newsletter, a circular, letters to editors, an interview, and a report. Arranged chronologically.
- Council Against Communist Aggression, 1950-1987. (Box No. 3-6.)
  Speeches (by William Green, Paul Douglas, Bertram Wolfe, Arthur McDowell, Thomas Dodd, Christopher Emmet, Herbert Philbrick and others), reports, correspondence, memoranda, newsletters, press releases. Arranged by physical form, and chronologically thereunder.
- Socialist Party File, 1921-1955. (Box No. 7-10.)
  Memoranda, agenda and minutes, resolutions, notes, printed articles, reports, statements, membership material, press releases, circulars, flyers, vote tallies, clippings, financial material, a copy of the New York State Socialist Party constitution, and fragments of an undated narrative, probably by Marx Lewis, describing the split in the New York State Socialist Party between left-wing and right-wing factions. Arranged by physical form.
- Victor Berger File, 1907-1967. (Box No. 10-12.)
  Correspondence, legal brief, speeches and statements, biographical material, chronology, reports, notes, memoranda, clippings, reports, draft legislation, transcripts, flyers, and miscellany. Most of this material relates to the effort to obtain Victor Berger's congressional salary for his widow, Meta Berger. Arranged by physical form.
- Subject File, 1918-1988. (Box No. 12-16.)
  Speeches, correspondence, newsletters, clippings, pamphlets, flyers, reports, printed articles, legal briefs, circulars, position statements, election materials, transcripts, draft legislation, press releases, interviews, notes, book reviews, biographical sketches, and resolutions. Arranged by subject.
- Increment (1989 Dec.), 1933-1988. (Box No. 17-26.)
  Hearing and broadcast transcripts, reports, correspondence, pamphlets, clippings, speeches and writings (by Marx Lewis), speeches and statements (by others), press releases, newsletters, and biographical material. Primarily printed material relating to various subjects, including labor, politics, and radicalism in the United States, foreign relations, religion, defense, communism, and terrorism.
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1926-1977.
  - Clippings, biographical sketches, and miscellany; includes material relating to the 1949 presidential inaguration. (Box 1., Folder 1)
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1916-1986
  - General, 1928-1984 (Box 1., Folder 2)
  - Berle, Adolph, 1960-1969 (Folder 3)
  - Borin, V.L., 1962-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Bridges, Harry, 1962 (Folder 5)
  - Buckley, William F., Jr., 1960-1964 (Folder 6)
  - Bundy, McGeorge, 1965 (Folder 7)
  - Cherne, Leo, 1966 (Folder 8)
  - Civiletti, Benjamin R., 1977 (Folder 9)
  - Darrow, Clarence, 1933-1934 (Folder 10)
  - Debs, Eugene V., 1916 (Folder 11)
  - DeToledano, Ralph, 1964 (Folder 12)
  - Dodd, Thomas J., 1960-1966 (Folder 13)
  - Douglas, Paul, 1958-1966 (Folder 14)
  - Emmet, Christopher, 1960 (Folder 15)
  - Ernst, Morris, 1970-1972 (Folder 16)
  - Green, William, 1952. Includes clippings and a letter from Alex Rose (Folder 17)
  - Hard, William, 1946-1947 (Folder 18)
  - Harriman, Averell, 1954 (Folder 19)
  - Helms, Jesse, 1986 (Folder 20)
  - Hornbeck, Stanley, 1957-1966 (Folder 21)
  - Irvine, Reed, 1971-1973 (Folder 22)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1960-1968 (Folder 23)
  - Judd, Walter, 1960-1976. Includes a prospectus (Folder 24)
  - Kampelman, Max, 1963 (Folder 25)
  - Kennedy, Edward, 1967 (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - Kennedy, John, 1961-1962 (Folder 2)
  - Kennedy, Robert, 1961-1968 (Folder 3)
  - Kornfeder, Joseph Z., 1963 (Folder 4)
  - Labin, Suzanne, 1962-1964 (Folder 5)
  - LaGuardia, Fiorello, 1932-1947. Includes an unpublished letter to the editor by Marx Lewis (Folder 6)
  - Levine, Isaac Don, 1961-1965 (Folder 7)
  - Lewis, Alfred Baker, 1929-1963 (Folder 8)
  - Lodge, John D., 1964 (Folder 9)
  - Lovestone, Jay, 1962-1965 (Folder 10)
  - Mayers, Henry (Cold War Council), 1963-1965 (Folder 11)
  - Meany, George, 1954-1965 (Folder 12)
  - Mondale, Walter, 1969 (Folder 13)
  - Mowrer, Edgar Ansel, 1960-1961 (Folder 14)
  - Mundt, Karl, 1959-1969 (Folder 15)
  - Nixon, Richard (Rosemary Woods), 1969 (Folder 16)
  - Nunn, Sam, 1983 (Folder 17)
  - Philbrick, Herbert A., 1960-1966 (Folder 18)
  - Pound, Roscoe, 1960 (Folder 19)
  - Randolph, A. Philip, 1960 (Folder 20)
  - Rauh, Joseph L., Jr., 1960 (Folder 21)
  - Regnery, Henry, 1965-1986 (Folder 22)
  - Reuther, Victor G., 1963 (Folder 23)
  - Robertson, Walter, 1954 (Folder 24)
  - Roosevelt, Edith Kermit, 1965 (Folder 25)
  - Roosevelt, Elliott, 1966 (Folder 26)
  - Roosevelt, James, 1966 (Folder 27)
  - Russell, Charles Edward, 1933-1935 (Folder 28)
  - Scott, Hugh, 1960 (Folder 29)
  - Sinclair, Upton, 1960 (Folder 30)
  - Singlaub, John (U.S. Council for World Freedom), 1985 (Folder 31)
  - Sprague, O.M.W., 1933-1934 (Folder 32)
  - Steele, Peter, 1963 (Folder 33)
  - Stevenson, Adlai, 1960 (Folder 34)
  - Stewart-Smith, D.G. (Foreign Affairs Circle), 1963-1965 (Folder 35)
  - Swarup, Ram (Asian People's Anti-Communist League), 1963-1965 (Folder 36)
  - Symms, Steve, 1986 (Folder 37)
  - Thomas, Norman, 1928-1984. Including clippings, memorandum, a letter to the editor by Norman Thomas, and miscellany (Folder 38)
  - Times (New York). Includes Arthur Krock, Hanson Baldwin, and Abe H. Raskin, 1962-1964 (Folder 39)
  - Wayne, John, 1960-1970 (Folder 40)
  - Weyl, Nathaniel, 1960-1964 (Folder 41)
  - White, William S., 1966 (Folder 42)
  - Wolfe, Bertram, 1972-1977. Includes a clipping (Folder 43)
  - Yorty, Samuel, 1962 (Folder 44)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1923-1986.
  - Typescripts, circular, newsletter, correspondence, printed copies, letters to editors, interview, and a report (Box 2., Folder 45)
- COUNCIL AGAINST COMMUNIST AGGRESSION, 1950-1987
  - General. Speeches (by William Green, Paul Douglas, Bertram Wolfe, Arthur McDowell, Thomas Dodd, Christopher Emmet, Herbert Philbrick and others), reports (by Marx Lewis and others), memoranda, press releases, pamphlets, clippings, newsletters (written by Marx Lewis and others), position statements, book reviews, and miscellany; includes material relating to the dismissal of Povl Bang-Jensen from the United Nations. SEE ALSO: SUBJECT FILE, part of which was apparently collected in the course of the Council's activities (Box 3.)
    - 1951-1958 (Folder 1-5)
    - 1959-1967 (Box 4., Folder 1-6)
    - 1968-1983 (Box 5., Folder 1-5)
  - Correspondence. Includes letters to Arthur Kohlberg, Dean Acheson, Rebecca West, William Henry Chamberlin, Charles Percy, Ronald Reagan, Moise Tshombe, John M. McCormack, Eleanor Roosevelt, William Fulbright, David Brinkley, Francis Walter, George Sokolsky, Victor Lasky, Thomas Kuchel, C. Dickerman Williams, Eugene McCarthy, Lawrence Fertig, John Foster Dulles, Milton Eisenhower, and William O. Douglas). Other individualized correspondence is included in the CORRESPONDENCE FILE
    - 1950-1955 (Folder 6)
    - 1956-1964 (Box 6., Folder 1-4)
    - 1965-1987 (Box 7., Folder 1-3)
- SOCIALIST PARTY, 1921-1955
  - General. Memoranda, agenda and minutes, resolutions, notes, printed articles (by Norman Thomas, Max Eastman and others), reports, statements, membership material, press releases, circulars, flyers, vote tallies, clippings, financial material, a copy of the New York State Socialist Party constitution, and fragments of an undated narrative by Marx Lewis (?) describing the split in the New York State Socialist Party between left-wing and right-wing factions (Box 7.)
    - Damaged material. Photocopies included below (Folder 4-5)
    - Undated (Box 8., Folder 1)
    - 1928-1935 July (Folder 2-4)
    - 1935 Aug.-1955 (Box 9., Folder 1-2)
  - Labor and Socialist Press Service (bulletin)
    - Damaged material. Photocopies included below (Folder 3)
    - 1933-1935 May (Folder 4-5)
    - 1935 June-1936 (Box 10., Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence. Includes Clarence Senior, Adolph Germer, and G. August Gerber, 1921-1936 (Folder 3)
- VICTOR BERGER FILE, 1907-1967
  - General (Box 10.)
    - Non-printed material. NOTE: Much of this material was written by Marx Lewis in an effort to obtain Victor Berger's congressional salary for his widow, Meta Berger. Legal brief, statements (by Bertrand Russell, Karl Kautsky and others), biographical material, chronology, reports, notes, memoranda on draft legislation, and miscellany, 1923-1934 (Folder 4)
    - Printed material. Clippings (including some material relating to the career of Meta Berger), reports, draft legislation, statement, flyers, and miscellany, 1907-1967 (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence
    - General. Includes Henry Allen Cooper and other congresspersons, and the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1927-1937 (Folder 6)
    - Berger, Meta. Includes correspondence with others, 1924-1944 (Folder 7)
    - Berger, Victor, 1924-1929 (Box 11., Folder 1)
    - Kautsky, Karl, 1931 (Folder 2)
    - Welles, Doris Berger and Elsa (Berger) Edelman, 1926-1944 (Folder 3)
  - Statement. Victor Berger to colleagues in Congress, 1919 April (Folder 4)
  - Transcripts
    - U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals, 1918 Oct., Vols. I-II (Folder 5-6)
    - U.S. Congress, 1919
      - General. Excerpts and notes by Marx Lewis, apparently intended for use in the preparation of a book (Box 12., Folder 1-2)
      - Hearings, Vols. I and II (Folder 3-4)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1988
  - General. Printed articles (by Jay Lovestone, Elliott Abrams and others), speech, transcripts, and conference material, 1933-1984 (Box 13., Folder 1)
  - Africa. Speeches, clippings, newsletters, pamphlets, flyer, reports, and printed articles, 1964-1968; primarily relates to South Africa (Folder 2)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Atheism. Clippings and a legal brief, 1926-1927 (Folder 3)
  - American Labor Party. Press release, clippings, circulars, position statements, and election materials, 1939-1944 (Folder 4)
  - Christian Anti-Communist Crusade. Correspondence, newsletters, flyers (including a memorandum by Victor Reuther), press release, and clippings, 1959-1985 (Folder 5)
  - Communism and anti-communism. Pamphlets, flyer, speech (by George Meany), educational material, and printed articles, 1961-1985 (Folder 6)
  - Defense and disarmament. Newsletters, correspondence, reports, radio broadcast transcripts, and a speech (by Thomas Dodd), 1960-1985 printed material, 1983-1987 (Folder 7)
  - Dialectical Studies Institute. Correspondence, reports, and printed material, 1983-1987 (Box 14., Folder 1)
  - Foreign affairs. Correspondence, speech, clippings, reports, newsletters, and printed articles (by Carl Sagan and others), 1959-1988 (Folder 2)
  - Freedom Academy. Newsletters, memoranda (including material relating to a meeting with Arthur Goldberg), draft copies of legislation, correspondence, position statements, reports, speeches, and clippings, 1959-1982 (Folder 3)
  - Fulbright, J. William. Pamphlets, clippings, correspondence (by J. William Fulbright and others), speeches (by Senator Fulbright and others), press releases, interview, notes, and newsletters, 1944-1983; primarily relates to foreign affairs, especially in Cuba and Vietnam correspondence, printed articles, and speeches (by Max Kampelman), c. 1969-1988; primarily relates to Russia SEE ALSO: Russia (Folder 4)
  - Human rights. Pamphlets, newsletters, clippings, reports, correspondence, printed articles, and speeches (by Max Kampelman), c. 1969-1988; primarily relates to Russia SEE ALSO: Russia (Box 15., Folder 1-2)
  - Intelligence and internal security
    - General. Clippings, newsletter, pamphlet, and speeches (by Larry McDonald), 1971-1978; includes material relating to the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Communist Party, and the Subversive Activities Control Board (Folder 3)
    - Central Intelligence Agency. Printed article, speeches and statements (by Larry McDonald, Reed Irvine and others), clippings, press releases, executive order, newsletters, book reviews, report, pamphlets, and a hearing transcript, 1974-1987; includes material relating to Philip Agee, and to the President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board (Folder 4)
    - Congressional committees. Fact sheets, letters to the editor, flyers, circulars, clippings, report, biographical sketches, speech, hearing transcript, and newsletters, 1960-1979; relates to both Senate and House Committees on Un-American Activities (Folder 5)
    - Violence and terrorism. Speeches and statements (by Larry McDonald and Frederick Schwarz), clippings, newsletters, hearing transcripts, reports, pamphlet, and a book review, 1974-1986 (Folder 6)
  - Journalism. Newsletters, form letter (by Jesse Helms), clippings, and a flyer, 1966-1985 (Folder 7)
  - Kennedy, Edward. Legal briefs, statements (by Robert Dole, Edward Kennedy and others), clippings, reports (including one by Lawrence Tribe), newsletter, and correspondence, 1982-1985; primarily relates to litigation involving the validity of the 1982 Massachusetts election (Box 16., Folder 1-2)
  - League for Industrial Democracy. Correspondence (with Jay Lovestone, Michael Harrington, Jack Valenti, and others), and clippings, 1965; includes material relating to Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) (Folder 3)
  - Liberal Party of New York State. Correspondence, circulars, biographical material, press releases, resolutions, brief statements (by Marx Lewis and others), and a flyer, 1944-1951 (Folder 4)
  - Lippmann, Walter. Clippings, printed articles, notes, correspondence, a letter to the editor (by Marx Lewis), a report, and a book review, 1965-1977; includes material relating to Vietnam (Folder 5)
  - Russia. Newsletters, radio broadcast transcripts, correspondence, press releases, printed articles (by Andrei Sakharov and others), speeches and statements, and clippings, 1961-1986. SEE ALSO: Human rights (Folder 6-7)
  - World War I. Notes relating to a meeting between President Wilson and Meyer London, a serial issue, and clippings (from a scrapbook assembled by Marx Lewis for Meyer London), 1914-1918; includes an article about Meyer London, material relating to the League of Nations, the Bolshevik revolution, the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk, U.S. intervention in Russia, and domestic war-related issues (Folder 8)
- INCREMENT (1989 Dec.), 1933-1988.
  - Hearing and broadcast transcripts, reports, correspondence, pamphlets, clippings, speeches and writings (by Marx Lewis), speeches and statements (by others), press releases, newsletters, and biographical material. Primarily printed material relating to various subjects, including labor, politics, and radicalism in the United States, foreign relations, religion, defense, communism, and terrorism (Box 17-26)